<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Anthony John C.</title>
  
  <subtitle>making things work</subtitle>
  <link href="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/"/>
  <updated>2025-12-24T03:03:52.494Z</updated>
  <id>https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Anthony John Caronongan</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Building my first Homelab Server</title>
    <link href="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/BuildingMyFirstHomeServer/"/>
    <id>https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/BuildingMyFirstHomeServer/</id>
    <published>2025-11-28T22:27:15.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-12-24T03:03:52.494Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the story of how I built my first homelab server for under <strong>AUD $60</strong>, what I planned to do with it, the problems I ran into, and what I learned along the way.</p><span id="more"></span><h2 id="The-Story"><a href="#The-Story" class="headerlink" title="The Story"></a>The Story</h2><p>One night, I was casually browsing eBay with no intention of buying anything. I came across an <strong>HP ProDesk 400 G2 SFF</strong> listed for <strong>$60</strong>. It came with an Intel i5-4590, 4GB of RAM, and a 1TB hard drive.</p><p>I knew this machine was never designed to be a server. It is a small office desktop built for basic work, not 24&#x2F;7 uptime. But for $60, it felt like the perfect machine to experiment on without worrying about damaging expensive hardware. I grabbed it immediately.</p><h2 id="The-Plan"><a href="#The-Plan" class="headerlink" title="The Plan"></a>The Plan</h2><p>Before even turning it on, I had a rough idea of what I wanted this server to do. Nothing fancy, just practical services I could actually use at home.</p><p>My goals were:</p><ul><li>Store files and backups</li><li>Run a network-wide ad blocker</li><li>Run Docker containers</li><li>Experiment with light AI models</li></ul><p>I also wanted this server to force me to learn Linux, networking, and system administration properly instead of relying on theory alone.</p><h2 id="Hardware-and-Upgrades"><a href="#Hardware-and-Upgrades" class="headerlink" title="Hardware and Upgrades"></a>Hardware and Upgrades</h2><p>The base specs were simple:</p><ul><li>HP ProDesk 400 G2 SFF</li><li>Intel i5-4590</li><li>4GB RAM</li><li>1TB HDD</li></ul><p>The first upgrade I made was adding a used <strong>128GB SSD</strong> from my old laptop as a boot drive. This alone made a huge difference. Boot times were faster, updates installed quicker, and the system felt far more responsive.</p><p>The original 1TB hard drive stayed in the system and was used for file storage.</p><h2 id="Choosing-an-Operating-System"><a href="#Choosing-an-Operating-System" class="headerlink" title="Choosing an Operating System"></a>Choosing an Operating System</h2><p>At first, I planned to run <strong>Proxmox</strong>. It is popular in the homelab community and seemed like the “correct” choice but I realised it’s not begginer friendly.</p><p>Instead, I installed a <strong>Ubuntu Server 24.04 LTS</strong> and run <strong>CasaOS</strong> on it. This kept resource usage low and made the system much simpler to manage.</p><h2 id="The-Setup"><a href="#The-Setup" class="headerlink" title="The Setup"></a>The Setup</h2><p>Since I didn’t want to keep a monitor and keyboard attached to a $40 PC sitting in the corner, my first priority was making it completely autonomous.</p><ul><li><p><strong>Networking &amp; Remote Access</strong> I needed to manage the server from my main laptop without it constantly “moving” around the network. I set a static IP on my router and enabled SSH immediately. This meant I could unplug the monitor 10 minutes after the first boot and never plug it back in.</p></li><li><p><strong>Headless Optimization</strong> Because this machine lives headless (no display), I had to ensure it could recover on its own if the power flickered. I tweaked the bootloader to skip graphical checks and set up an automated login. Now, when I hit the power button, it’s ready to accept commands instantly without waiting for a user to sign in physically.</p></li><li><p><strong>CasaOS Integration</strong> I didn’t want to spend my life staring at a command line. I installed CasaOS to give the server a friendly, visual dashboard. It acts as the “face” of the homelab, making it easy to manage Docker containers and check system health at a glance.</p></li><li><p><strong>Storage &amp; Sharing</strong> To make use of that 1TB drive, I set up Samba for file sharing. The tricky part was configuring it to play nice with both my Windows gaming PC and my MacBook. After some tweaking, I have a reliable network share that works seamlessly across different operating systems for backups and media.</p></li><li><p><strong>Ad-Blocking</strong> I deployed Pi-hole to act as a network-wide ad blocker. It’s not magic—some stubborn ads (like on YouTube) still sneak through—but it has significantly cleaned up the web browsing experience on my phone and tablet without needing browser extensions.</p></li><li><p><strong>Local AI Experiments</strong> This was the most fun part. I’m using <strong>Belullama</strong>, a fantastic tool that bundles Ollama and OpenWebUI together. Instead of wrestling with Python scripts in a terminal to run AI models, this gives me a clean, ChatGPT-like interface. It allows me to easily download and test different models right from the browser.</p></li></ul><blockquote><p>I’ve documented every command, config file I used. You can find the full technical breakdown here:<br><a href="https://github.com/anthnyjhn/HP-Prodesk400G2-Server"><strong>Detailed Setup Guide on GitHub</strong></a></p></blockquote><h2 id="Power-Efficiency"><a href="#Power-Efficiency" class="headerlink" title="Power Efficiency"></a>Power Efficiency</h2><img src="powerdraw.jpg" width="300" alt="Average power draw"><p>One of my main concerns was how much this would cost to run 24&#x2F;7. Surprisingly, the machine is incredibly efficient. It averages a power draw of just <strong>22W</strong>, which totals around <strong>15 kWh per month</strong>. At current rates, that adds only about ~<strong>AUD $4.60</strong> to my monthly electricity bill. Considering the utility it provides, I’d say it’s worth every penny.</p><p>I use Meross smart plug to monitor energy consumption and so I can remotely shutdown or turn on my server.</p><h2 id="Final-Thoughts"><a href="#Final-Thoughts" class="headerlink" title="Final Thoughts"></a>Final Thoughts</h2><p>This server isn’t a powerhouse. It’s not going to win any benchmark competitions, and it certainly isn’t built for enterprise-grade workloads but it works. It sits quietly in the corner blocking ads, backing up my files, and running my services without complaint.</p><p>If you have been thinking about starting a homelab, don’t wait for the “perfect” gear. Just start. You will learn infinitely more by building than you ever will by just reading about it.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the story of how I built my first homelab server for under &lt;strong&gt;AUD $60&lt;/strong&gt;, what I planned to do with it, the problems I ran into, and what I learned along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="Projects" scheme="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/categories/Projects/"/>
    
    
    <category term="homelab" scheme="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/tags/homelab/"/>
    
    <category term="linux" scheme="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/tags/linux/"/>
    
    <category term="server" scheme="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/tags/server/"/>
    
    <category term="docker" scheme="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/tags/docker/"/>
    
    <category term="self-hosting" scheme="https://blog.anthnyjhn.com/tags/self-hosting/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
